A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia 1919-1925
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia 1919-1925
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.472 VI
This collection consists of ca. 10,500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
Archival transfer, Office of the President, 1947 March 4, 1947 May 7.
Biographical/Historical Information
Prior to 1904, the University of Virginia did not have a president, the chief administrative officer was the Chairman of the Faculty.
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by Edwin Anderson Alderman, the first president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Contents List
- "A-Am" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 1)
  references to American Council on Education
- "An-Ay" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 1)
- Academic Schools - Miscellaneous 1922-1924 (Box 1)
- Administrative Council 1921-1925 (Box 1)
- Advertising 1921-1925 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board - Endowment Fund 1922 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board - Finance Committee 1922-1925 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board - General Correspondence 1921-1925 (Box 1)
  references to Carnegie Endowment
- Alumni Board - Investments 1922-1925 (Box 1)
- Alumni Board - Meetings 1920-1925 (Box 2)
  (2 folders)
- Alumni Board - Treasurer 1919-1925 (Box 2)
  (3 folders)
- Alumni Office - Secretary 1922-1925 (Box 2)
- Anglo-American Foundation 1925 Jan-Jun (Box 3)
- Annual Reports 1919-1925 (Box 2)
- Applications for Positions 1919-1925 Jun (Box 3)
- Art, Architecture and Music 1919-1925 (Box 3)
  references to tax on art sales
- Articles about the University 1921-1925 (Box 3)
  references to advocating a poor man's education
- Assocation of American Universities 1919-1924 (Box 4)
- Astronomy 1922-1925 (Box 4)
- Athletic Committee 1920-1925 (Box 4)
- "B" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 4)
- Barbour-Page Lectures 1920-1925 (Box 4)
- Biblical History and Literature 1922-1924 (Box 4)
- Biology, references to Botanical Society 1920-1925 (Box 4)
- Blandy Farm bequest 1923-1924 (Box 4)
- Budget Statements 1921-1923 (Box 4)
  includes balance sheets
- Buildings and Grounds - Fraternity Houses 1922-1923 (Box 5)
- Buildings and Grounds - Gymnasium 1921-1925 (Box 5)
- Buildings and Grounds - Superintendent's Office 1920-1925 (Box 5)
- Buildings and Grounds - University Bookstore 1923-1924 (Box 5)
- "C" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 5)
- Caps and Gowns 1923-1925 (Box 5)
- Carnegie Foundation 1920-1925 (Box 5)
- Centennial - Acknowledgement for Commemorative Medals 1921 May - Jun (Box 5)
- Centennial - Anniversaries of Other Educational Institutions 1909-1921 (Box 5)
- Centennial Correspondence 1920-1921 (Box 5)
  1 of 5
- Centennial Correspondence 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  2-5 of 5
- Centennial - Endowment Fund 1921-1925 (Box 6)
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (1 of 26) references to Dinner Speakers
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (2 of 26) references to Delegates
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (3 of 26) references to Orchestra
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (4 of 26) references to Religious Address
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (5 of 26) references to Clergymen
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (6 of 26) references to Reception
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (7 of 26) references to Registration
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (8 of 26) references to Medical Alumni
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (9 of 26) references to Teaching Alumni
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (10 of 26) references to Alumni Barbecue
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (11 of 26) references to Engineering Alumni
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (12 of 26) references to Alumni Directory
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 6)
  (13 of 26) references to Medical Department Meeting
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (14 of 26) references to Law Alumni
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (15 of 26) references to Distinguished Guests
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (16 of 26) references to Formal Dinner
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (17 of 26) references to Programs and Invitations
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (18 of 26) references to Entertainment
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (19 of 26) references to Housing and Feeding
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (20 of 26) references to Reunion of World War Alumni
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (21 of 26) references to Band Concert
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (22 of 26) references to University Pageant
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (23 of 26) references to Mrs. Gaither's letters
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (24 of 26) references to Mrs. Kepner's letters
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (25 of 26) references to Centennial Program
- Centennial - Faculty and Staff - Responsibilities 1920-1921 (Box 7)
  (26 of 26) references to Pilgrimage to Monticello
- Centennial - Lists of Hosts and Hostesses, Committee Members and Special Guests 1921 (Box 8)
- Centennial - Printed Matter 1921 (Box 8)
- Centennial - Replies from American Colleges and Universities 1921 (Box 8)
- Centennial - Replies from Foreign Universities 1921 Feb - Jun (Box 8)
- Centennial - Replies from Individuals 1921 Jan - Jun (Box 8)
- Centennial - Replies from Institutions 1921 Apr - May (Box 9)
- Centennial - Replies from Virginia Colleges 1921 Jan - Jun (Box 9)
- Centennial Celebration Statement of Cost 1921 Jun (Box 9)
- Centennial Statistical Information 1919 (Box 9)
- Centennial Tentative Program Drafts and Cost Estimates 1920-1921 (Box 9)
- Centennial - The University of Virginia in Service of the Republicn.d. (Box 9)
- Chemistry, references to prize contests 1920-1925 (Box 9)
- Commerce and Business Administration, references to establishment of McIntire School 1919-1925 (Box 9)
- Commons 1920-1925 (Box 9)
- Commons 1920-1925 (Box 9)
- Convocations 1921-1925 (Box 9)
- "D" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 10)
- Distinguished Students 1923 (Box 10)
- "E" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 10)
- Economics 1919-1925 (Box 10)
- Education 1919-1925 (Box 10)
  references to Charlottesville Education Statistics
- Education - General Education Board - Docket 1919 Dec (Box 10)
- Engineering 1919-1925 (Box 10)
  references to Committee on Engineering Experiment Station Legislation
- English 1920-1925 (Box 10)
- Exchange Professors - Southern Universities 1924 Jan (Box 10)
- "Fa-Fo" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 10)
  list of faculty, references to Faculty Committee
- "Fr-Fy" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 10)
- Faculty - resignations of Professors Lefevre, Pott, and Howze 1925 May - Jun (Box 11)
  references to Prohibition Offenses
- Faculty - resignations of Professors Lefevre, Pott, and Howze 1925 Jun - Jul (Box 11)
  references to Docket
- Faculty - resignations of Professors Lefevre, Pott, and Howze 1925 (Box 11)
  references to Student Petitions
- Faculty - resignations of Professors Lefevre, Pott, and Howze 1925 Jun - Jul (Box 11)
  references to letters following action
- Fellowship in Memory of Craig Woodrow McDonald 1923 Apr (Box 11)
- Fellowships and Scholarships 1919-1925 (Box 11)
- Finals 1919-1925 (Box 11)
- Forestry 1921-1925 (Box 11)
- Forms 1919-1925 (Box 11)
  (1 of 2)
- Forms 1922-1925 (Box 12)
  (2 of 2)
- Founder's Day 1920-1925 (Box 12)
- "G" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 12)
  Institute of Politics and Guggenheim Foundation
- Geological Survey 1924-1925 (Box 12)
- Geology 1920-1925 (Box 12)
- Germanic Languages 1922 (Box 12)
- Gifts 1919-1925 (Box 12)
  establishment of Whitehead Scholarship Fund
- "Ha-Hi" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 13)
  references to heating plant
- "Ho-Hy" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 13)
- Harman Foundation 1922-1924 (Box 13)
- Higher Education 1920-1925 (Box 13)
  (5 folders)
- Higher Education Committee Budget 1922-1923 (Box 13)
- Higher Education Committee Minutes 1923-1924 (Box 13)
- Higher Education: Statistics 1922-1924 (Box 14)
- History 1921-1925 (Box 14)
- Honor System 1920-1925 (Box 14)
- Honors - Intermediate and Final 1923 Apr (Box 14)
- "I-J" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 14)
  references to Prohibition
- Instructors and Assistants 1920-1924 (Box 14)
- "K" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 14)
- "L" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 14)
  references to Financial Aid
- Latin 1921-1924 (Box 14)
- Law Department 1921-1925 (Box 14)
- Law - Teaching Staff 1920-1924 (Box 14)
- Legislative Docket 1919-1922 (Box 15)
  (4 folders)
- Legislative Program 1920-1924 (Box 15)
- Library 1920-1925 (Box 15)
  references to University in WW
- Loan Funds 1921 Sep (Box 15)
- "Mc" Miscellaneous 1920-1925 (Box 16)
- "Ma-Mi" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 16)
  report on Mental Hygeine
- "Mo-My" Miscellaneous 1921-1925 (Box 16)
  bibliography of Monroe Doctrine
- McIntire Fund 1921-1925 (Box 16)
  schedule of Sales and Purchases involving McIntire Fund
- Mathematics 1921-1924 (Box 16)
- Medical Department 1920-1925 (Box 16)
- Medical College Transfer 1920-1924 (Box 16)
  1-2 of 9
- Medical College Transfer 1920-1924 (Box 17)
  3-9 of 9
- Medicine - Chair of Nursing 1923-1925 (Box 18)
- Medicine - Miscellaneous 1923-1925 (Box 18)
- Medicine - Public Health 1922-1925 (Box 18)
- Medical, School of - Hospital 1919-1925 (Box 18)
  (1 of 3)
- Medical, School of - Hospital 1923-1925 (Box 18)
  (2 of 3), references to University of Virginia Ward Patient Statistics
- Medical, School of - Hospital 1919-1925 (Box 18)
  (3 of 3), references to Superintendent's Reports
- Memorial Tablet for the Virginia Signers of the Declaration of Independence in the Senate Chamber, Richmond, Virginia 1920-1924 (Box 18)
- Military Instruction - ROTC 1919-1924 (Box 18)
- "N" Miscellaneous 1920-1925 (Box 18)
- National Association of State Universities 1920-1925 (Box 18)
- "O-P" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 19)
- Phi Beta Kappa 1922-1925 (Box 19)
  2 folders
- Philosophy 1921-1922 (Box 19)
- Physical Education 1923-1925 (Box 19)
- Physics 1919-1925 (Box 19)
- Political Science 1921-1925 (Box 19)
- Psychology 1922-1925 (Box 19)
- Public Speaking 1922-1924 (Box 19)
- Public Welfare 1923
- Purchasing Agent 1922 (Box 19)
- Purnell Bill 1925 (Box 19)
  granting funds to Agricultural Experiment Stations
- "Q-Ra" Miscellaneous 1922-1925 (Box 19)
- "Rea-Ref" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 19)
- "Rel-Rey" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 19)
  radio broadcasting, art tax
- "Ri-Ry" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 19)
- "Ri-Ry" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 19)
- Religious Exercises at the University 1920-1925 (Box 19)
- Research 1922-1925 (Box 19)
  references to Academy of Science
- Rhodes Scholarships 1919-1924 (Box 19)
- Romance Languages 1920-1925 (Box 20)
- Rural Sociology 1924-1925 (Box 20)
- "Sa-Si" Miscellaneous 1920-1925 (Box 20)
  references to Near East Relief Organization
- "Sk-Sy" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 20)
- Southern Exposition 1924-1925 (Box 20)
- Student Drinking 1920-1925 (Box 20)
- Statistics and Facts 1919-1925 (Box 20)
- Summer Session 1919-1925 (Box 20)
- Summer Work 1920-1925 (Box 20)
- "T-U" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 20)
  references to Alumni Endowment
- Term Reports 1922-1925 (Box 21)
- University Extension 1920-1925 (Box 21)
- University Houses, applications for 1923-1924 (Box 21)
- "V" Miscellaneous 1920-1925 (Box 21)
- Virginia Quarterly Review 1921-1925 (Box 21)
- Visitors, Board of - Meetings 1918-1925 (Box 21)
  (1-2 of 3)
- Visitors, Board of - Meetings 1924-1925 (Box 22)
  (3 of 3)
- Visitors, Board of - Membership 1919-1925 (Box 22)
- Visitors, Board of - Docket 1920 Jan - Feb (Box 22)
- "W-Z" Miscellaneous 1919-1925 (Box 22)
- William H. White - Foundation 1923-1925 (Box 22)
- Women's College 1919-1924 (Box 22)
- Woodrow Wilson Memorial Tablet 1925 Mar - Jun (Box 22)